Guide to the Walter Chauncey Camp Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Walter Chauncey Camp papers
1870-1983
1870-1925
MS 125
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
32.25
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs and family papers, and document Walter Camp's devotion to sports and in particular to football, which form he greatly modified. In his voluminous correspondence with Yale football stars, players at other universities, football coaches and sports associations, the interpretation of football rules forms one of the principal topics of correspondence. Prominent figures include George A. Adee, Thomas L. McClung, Vance D. McCormick, S. Brinckerhoff Thorne, Ray Tompkins, Alonzo Stagg and Fielding H. Yost. Camp's interest in physical fitness was put into action during World War I when he organized exercise programs for elderly men, a special program for Washington officials, and ultimately developed his "Daily Dozen" exercises for the Navy. These activities are reflected in his correspondence with Newton D. Baker, Josephus Daniels, John W. Davis, William G. McAdoo, Franklin D. Roosevelt and William Howard Taft. He also corresponded with Theodore Roosevelt, 1905 and 1908, in connection with a commission set up to investigate fatalities in football during the season of 1905. Approximately twelve feet of the papers are made up of Camp's writings, which include articles, rule manuals, reviews and books. Half the material is devoted to football and another large section is on physical fitness.
Camp, Walter, 1859-1925
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection, with the exception of Accession 1999-M-138 and Accession 2007-M-067, is available on microfilm, and patrons must use FILM HM 137 instead of the originals.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alice Sumner Camp, 1926, and Janet Camp Troxell, 1978-1980; transfer from the Preservation Department, 1990; transfer from the Department of Athletics, 2007.
Existence and Location of Copies
Entire collection, with the exception of Accession 1999-M-138, also available on microfilm (46,204 frames on 48 reels, 35 mm.) from Scholarly Resources, Inc., Wilmington, Delaware.
Accession 1999-M-138 also available as negative film for reproduction; SML, Microform; Film B7032:5.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series and two additions: I. Correspondence. II. Writings. III. Newspaper and Magazine Clippings. IV. Photographs. V. Family Papers.
Scope and Contents
Five series comprise the Walter Camp Papers: Series I, Correspondence, Series II, Writings, Series III, Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, Series IV, Photographs, and Series V, Family Papers. The material covers the approximate period 1875 - 1925, an historic period of fifty years in the development of sports, particularly football. The papers have been microfilmed and the microfilm arrangement is described in Appendix A.
Replying to a question, "What is your hobby today", in a questionnaire from The Select Features Company (presumably around 1890), Walter Camp answered, "Athletics and physical fitness," and it is interesting that his correspondence, in Series I - indeed most of the other series as well - deal principally with these two general subjects.
Camp corresponded with many Yale football stars on matters concerning football, including George A. Adee, Burr Chamberlin, William H. Corbin, Robert N. Corwin, Charles O. Gill, Frank A. Hinkey, T. A. D. Jones, Malcolm L. McBride, Thomas L. McClung, Vance D. McCormick, Fred T. Murphy, Thomas L. Shevlin, Jr., S. Brinckerhoff Thorne and Ray Tompkins. Others, on the interpretation of football rules, were William S. Langford, H. E. Van Surdam, Henry M. Wheaton, Benjamin Ide Wheeler, H. S. White and Fielding H. Yost. He kept in close touch with prominent members of the football rules committee, James A. Babbitt, John C. Bell, Paul J. Dashiell, Parke H. Davis, L. M. Dennis, J. B. Fine, E. K. Hall, Percy Haughton, ALexander Moffat, W. M. Morice, W. T. Reid, Alonzo A. Stagg, H. L. Williams and Robert D. Wrenn. And noteworthy is his correspondence with President Theodore Roosevelt during the critical years when the game of football faced the prospect of being outlawed because of brutality.
Camp's interest in coaching football led to much correspondence with famous coaches throughout the country, Burr Chamberlin (Stanford University), Percy D. Haughton (Harvard University), John W. Heisman (Georgia Institute of Technology), T.A.D. Jones (Yale University), William W. Roper (Princeton University), Alonzo A. Stagg (University of Chicago), Glenn S. Warner (United States Indian School and the University of Pittsburgh) and Fielding H. Yost (University of Michigan).
On the sometimes strained Yale-Harvard athletic relations, Harvard alumni correspondents included: Professor James Barr Ames, dean of the Harvard Law School; Lebaron R. Briggs, dean of Harvard College and president of Radcliffe College; Lorin Deland, a Boston attorney who collaborated with Camp on the book, Football; W. Cameron Forbes, a prominent businessman in Boston, author of articles on athletics for Collier's Weekly and Outing and later ambassador to Japan; James J. Storrow, Boston attorney and banker; and Mark Sullivan, an editor of Collier's Weekly and noted author and commentator.
Among the Yale alumni with whom Camp corresponded on general athletics were Eugene Lamb Richards, professor of mathematics, director of the Yale gymnasium and author of articles on Yale athletics, and Samuel J. Elder, prominent Boston lawyer and president of the Boston Bar Association, whose letters brought news of athletics at Harvard.
The subject of physical fitness, in which Camp had a life-long interest, led to correspondence with prominent political figures in Washington, including Newton D. Baker, Josephus Daniels, John W. Davis, Franklyn K. Lane, William G. McAdoo, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Daniel C. Roper and John Q. Tilson, in connection with the founding of the Senior Service Corps. Through these political contacts he corresponded with many government departments on this subject, including the departments of Agriculture, Commerce, Labor, Navy, the Interior, Treasury and War, and the Tariff Commission, Locally, in New Haven, where the Senior Service Corps was founded, Camp kept in contact with two men who provided leadership for the corps, Professor William Howard Taft (ex-president) and Col. Isaac M. Ullman, president of the New Haven Chamber of Commerce.
Involved continuously in Yale matters, Camp corresponded with important figures including Arthur T. Hadley, Henry B. Sargent, Charles Seymour, Charles H. Sherrill, Anson Phelps Stokes, Theodore S. Woolsey, Henry P. Wright and William Burnet Wright, Jr. He consulted with Samuel J. Fiske and George S. Mason on legal matters affecting Yale. There is also considerable correspondence on the subject of Yale athletic programs with the Yale Field Corporation, Yale Financial Union, the Yale University Athletic, Baseball, and Football Associations, the Yale University Boat Club, the Secretary's office and the Treasurer's office.
Camp was in contact with his book publishers: A. G. Spalding & Bros., American Sports Publishing Company, Byron G. Moon & Company, Charles Scribner's Sons, D. Appleton & Company, D. C. Heath & Company, Doubleday, Page & Company, Harper & Bros., Herbert W. Fisher, Moffat, Yard & Company and the Platt & Peck Company. There is also much correspondence with magazines carrying Camp's articles: Baseball Magazine, Boy's Magazine, Century, Collier's Weekly, Golf Illustrated, Outing, St. Nicholas, Saturday Evening Post, Vanity Fair, Women's Home Companion, World's Work, the Yale Alumni Weekly and Youth's Companion. Correspondence with well-known newspapers included the Boston Globe, New York Herald, Philadelphia Press, the Week's Sport and the Yale Daily News.
Prominent among the authors with whom Camp corresponded were: Silas Bent, editor and promoter of a syndicated house-organ series of industrial pamphlets on good health habits; Alfred S. Eyre, author of articles for Collier's Weekly; Norman Hapgood, a Collier's Weekly editor; William Heyliger, who syndicated Camp's articles on special sporting subjects and collaborated on the book Danny the Freshman; Harford Powel, Jr., an editor of Collier's Weekly and Camp's authorized biographer; H. G. Salsinger, sporting editor of the Detroit News and one of Camp's contacts with football players in the Middle West; and Caspar Whitney with whom Camp had a long association, first on The Week's Sport in the 1880's and then at Outing and Collier's Weekly, and Harper & Brothers.
Walter Camp's correspondence in Series I includes a considerable amount of material, minutes, committee reports, agreements, contracts, etc., which bears on the subject of the correspondence. Consult Appendix B for details.
Another question in the questionnaire referred to above was, "What was your ambition when you were a boy?" Camp replied, "To write." It would appear that this ambition was realized during his lifetime, for Series II, WRITINGS, constitutes a major section in the Walter Camp Papers. Most of the articles are typescripts and undated except for the Consolidated Press pieces. The Consolidated Press articles, exclusive press releases on football and general athletics, were syndicated, usually twice a week, by the Consolidated Press Association of Washington, D. C., to many newspapers throughout the country during the 1920's.
Approximately one-half of the writings are concerned with football, its history, reviews of the seasons, All-America teams and rules. Although not complete, the series includes most of the football rules and guide books, dating back to 1876, most written by Camp. Included also is the investigating committee questionnaire and report in 1893-1894. The study was designed to weigh the benefits, both mentally and physically, of the game of football against the injuries sustained. The questionnaire was mailed by Camp to approximately 1,200 football players and coaches in the United States, and to headmasters of many preparatory and high schools. The report concluded that football was of marked benefit, the injuries trivial, and with improvements called for in the general conduct of the game, football was one of the best sports in America.
Camp's writings on other sports include rugby, baseball, track, golf, rowing and tennis, and a few articles on women in sports and athletics in general. The remainder of this series consists of writings on physical fitness, the Daily Dozen, [1] the Senior Service Corps, playgrounds and recreation, general articles on the game of bridge, clocks, Yale College and the Yale Bowl, and Camp's poems and aphorisms.
Series III contains the newspaper and magazine clippings which Walter Camp collected from the local press and from subscription clipping services across the country. Difficulties in processing these clippings -- some over one hundred years old -- were experienced due to the deterioration of the newsprint, but an estimated 90 per cent have been preserved on microfilm. The material supplements, and in some cases duplicates in printed form, Camp's writings as described in Series II. Unfortunately, many of the clippings are undated.
This series is important not only for articles written by Camp which otherwise might have been lost, but for editorial comment and photographs illustrating the subject. There are also many clippings of articles by Caspar Whitney and other noted journalists and columnists about Camp, or about subjects in which he was interested. No doubt many of the clippings served as research notes for his own articles.
Interesting material not found elsewhere in the Camp Papers is among the clippings. His false arrest in New York City in 1887, which caused considerable apprehension, is described fully. The memorable Walter Camp dinner in New York in Madison Square Garden in 1892, when he was presented with the beautiful Tiffany sterling silver cup [2] by Yale alumni and others, is reported in detail.
There are many clippings on the death of Walter Camp in 1925. The most complete collection on this subject, however, is in a bound scrapbook which was presented to Mrs. Camp by her friends, Mary and Charles Goodrich, and will be found in Series V, Family Papers.
Series IV, Photographs, contains several photographs of Camp as an undergraduate and in later years. Included is the frequently used photograph of him as captain of the football team, standing at the Yale fence, and several photos of Camp with other people, including the football rules committee, and with Guy Nickalls, noted Yale rowing coach.
Other subjects of photographs include the Daily Dozen and physical fitness groups, notably the "Walter Scamps" in Washington during World War I. Among the Senior Service Corps photos are two of ex-president William Howard Taft and Col. Isaac M. Ullman with Mr. Camp.
The majority of sports photographs are of football and include games, teams and players of several universities and colleges, and shots taken at football practice. Photographs of other sports include baseball, golf, rowing and track, although the actual number is not large.
The final series in the Walter Camp Papers contains the family papers, few in number but of interest historically. There is some biographical material and a few pages of a diary kept by Camp as an undergraduate. It also includes his notes on trips to England in 1899 and 1907 mixed with printed travel literature and memorabilia.
This series also contains scattered correspondence of Mrs. Walter Camp's over the period 1884 - 1934. There are a few letters from the Yale football stars she met as her husband's emissary at football practice, notably Ted Coy, Frank Hinkey, Tad Jones, Lee McClung, Vance McCormick and Ray Tompkins. The files include letters from friends: Julian W. Curtiss, Arthur T. Hadley, E. K. Hall, Mr. and Mrs. Averill Harriman, Guy Nickalls, Caspar Whitney and Mr. and Mrs. Orville Wright and conclude with letters from friends interested in the Walter Camp Memorial.
Family Papers also includes some correspondence of Mr. and Mrs. Walter Camp, Jr., from 1907 - 1925, and one folder of correspondence of Mrs. John C. English, mother-in-law of Walter Camp, Jr., from 1883 - 1923. Included are three bound scrapbooks. One contains letters of condolence to Mrs. Walter Camp in connection with her husband's death, the second consists of the telegrams she received at that time, and the third, a gift of friends, has a great many clippings of press notices and obituaries.
In this series, too, under the classification "Memorabilia", is printed material, mostly programs, of athletic contests including baseball, boxing, football, golf, Olympic games, rowing, tennis, track, athletics in general, and Yale College events during Camp's lifetime.
Many feature stories about Walter Camp have appeared in football programs and Yale alumni publications, national magazines, and in one case the American Heritage Magazine of History. After Camp's death members of the family continued to collect these stories. These are also included in Series V, Family Papers.
Series V concludes with personal correspondence of Walter Camp's daughter, Janet Troxell, from 1928 - 1980. Among her papers are several folders with her correspondence and research notes in connection with her controversy with Tim Cohane, author of The Yale Football Story. Mr. Cohane had written that the idea of the "All-America Team" selections originated in 1889 with Caspar Whitney, manager of The Week's Sport newspaper, not with Walter Camp. Naturally Mrs. Troxell resented the inference that her father was dishonest and untruthful in claiming credit for an idea not his own. Mrs. Troxell spent many hours in 1951 and 1952 researching her father's papers at the Yale University Library to dispute the claim of Mr. Cohane, and prove as far as possible that the idea for the "All-America Team" was in fact Walter Camp's. A copy of the book, The Yale Football Story, with her notes on several pages, is included here.
The papers of Walter Camp came to the Yale University Library in 1926, the gift of his widow, Alice Sumner Camp. They do not include any business correspondence or other material concerning the New Haven Clock Company, nor will researchers find any references to Camp's business career. Starting in 1978, Walter Camp's daughter, Janet Camp Troxell, has augmented her father's papers with a quantity of material important to the background of the Camp family.
[1] Four sets of the victrola records containing the Daily Dozen exercises were transferred to the Historical Sound Recordings Collection.
[2] This cup, one of Camp's prize possessions, was recently included in the"Champion of American Sports" exhibition at the Smithsonian Institution, organized by the National Portrait Gallery in Washington, which opened on June 22, 1981.
Biographical / Historical
Walter Camp, 1859 - 1925
Considered the foremost authority on American athletics, and one who bent his energies successfully for many years toward the formation of clean sports, Walter Camp was probably the best all-around amateur athlete of his time. Famous among college coaches and the orginator of the Daily Dozen series of short-hand exercises for physical fitness, he combined success in athletics with success in business and in letters.
Walter Camp led a double life. Athletes and college men were proud to point to him as their inspiration and example, and business men hailed him as equally luminous in their sphere as head of the New Haven Clock Company, one of the largest manufacturing concerns in Connecticut at that time. His interests were on the financial and selling side rather than in the factory. Few college men knew that Camp had a business side and the business men, who didn't read the sporting pages, had no idea that he was extensively involved in athletics. Born in New Britain, Connecticut, on April 7, 1859, Walter Camp was the only child of Leverett Lee Camp, a school teacher and publisher, and Ellen Cornwell, daughter of Chauncey Cornwell, both of New Britain. Walter's middle name which he seldom used was Chauncey, His earliest known ancestor was Nicholas Camp, who came to the United States about 1630 from Essex County, England, and settled in Milford, Connecticut.
Following the death of Mr. Cornwell, Camp's maternal grandfather, in 1863, the Camp family moved to 170 Chapel Street, New Haven, and Leverett became principal of the Washington School. About three years later they moved to 595 Chapel Street at which time Leverett was principal of the Dwight School. In 1884 the family moved again, to 1303 Chapel Street. at 1 Walter lived at home until his marriage in 1888.
Camp prepared at Hopkins Grammar School, a noted institution founded in 1660, predating Yale College. It was located at that time on the northwest corner of High and Wall Streets where the Yale Law School is today. Camp usually stood 4th, 5th or 6th in a class of thirty-three. He entered Yale in 1876 and graduated in 1880 with an A.B. degree. As an undergraduate he was a member of Delta Kappa (a freshman Society), He Boule' (a sophomore Society), the Delta Kappa Epsilon fraternity and Skull and Bones.
Captain of the freshman baseball and football teams, Camp made several varsity teams while at Yale. He was an outstanding pitcher on the baseball nine, and one of the first to master the art of pitching a curve with a baseball. He also played shortstop and left field. He held the best individual record in fielding for shortstops in the old intercollegiate league (.897) and in batting (.627). His fame as a college player led to an offer, in 1884, by the National League of Baseball Clubs to become a member of the staff of league umpires. He was on the track team and is credited at Yale with inventing the hurdle step which was the beginning of the present technique of running instead of jumping hurdles. He rowed on the class crew, and won swimming races from short distances to five miles. He was a fine golfer and tennis player. But it was football that was to make him famous.
The first game of college football under the old Rugby Union rules adopted by Yale and Harvard was played between Yale and Harvard in 1876, and Camp played half-back. This was the year he entered college, and though only seventeen years old, he made the team. Strong, quick with his hands and feet and a fast runner, he had a reputation as a good long distance punter and drop and place kicker. Two years later (1878) he was captain of the team, and again captain in 1879. Elected for the third time in 1880, while a student at the Yale Medical School, he stepped aside so that his friend Robert W. Watson, could be captain. In 1881, Franklin M. Eaton was captain but broke his collarbone in practice and Camp became captain for the third time. In 1882 a knee injury in practice ended Camp's playing days.
As an undergraduate, Walter Camp's creative mind devised the "eleven", the "safety" as a scoring play, the "scrimmage" and the "quarterback." The year he was made captain of the team he attended the second convention of the old Intercollegiate Football Association which was then the football rules legislature. The change from fifteen to eleven players was proposed in 1878 and the safety as a scoring play in 1879. Both proposals were adopted the following year. It was at this same convention in 1880 that Camp succeeded in having the "scrimmage" adopted, probably the greatest single invention that had been made in any game. The old Rugby "scrum" gave neither side the orderly possession of the ball nor the right to put it into play. Camp's "scrimmage" gave the holder of the ball undisputed possession, and the player who received the ball from the snap-back was called the "quarterback".
With his strong interest in anatomy, Camp entered the Yale Medical School in the fall of 1880. After two years, and passing all but two subjects for the M.D. degree, he left school, noting in a biographical questionnaire that "the death of a surgeon with whom I had expected to practice medicine caused me to leave the medical school and go into business."
Upon leaving medical school, Walter Camp joined the sales department of the Manhattan Watch Company in New York City. After a year he was employed as a salesman in the New York office of the New Haven Clock Company. He steadily progressed through the selling end to the export department and thence to the position of assistant treasurer in the New Haven main office. He became treasurer and general manager in 1902, president in 1903, and finally chairman of the board.
In 1888, Camp married Alice Graham Sumner, sister of William Graham Sumner, noted professor of political and social science at Yale, They had two children, Walter Camp, Jr. (1891) and Janet Camp Troxell (1897).
Following graduation from Yale, Camp became deeply involved in intercollegiate football and for thirty years was known as the outstanding football legislator and coach in America. He was a member of every football rules committee and convention until his death, a period of almost fifty years. Although he never coached a Yale team, he was Yale's "advisory coach," a coach of the coaches, the unpaid chief mentor and arbiter. And when his clock business interfered, another Camp got into the coaching act; his wife "Allie" Camp attended daily practice. Notebook in hand, she trotted up and down the sidelines and every evening gave Walter a detailed rundown on what each player had done, or failed to do. Their house became Yale's nocturnal football headquarters for discussions and strategies with the football captain and key players.